All you got to do is watch this video
and follow along and it's going to
unlock Resolve for you. If you're brand
new to making videos in Resolve, this is
the perfect place to start. And if you
find yourself feeling overwhelmed
because Resolve is such a huge program,
we're going to cut out all the stuff you
don't need to know and we're just going
to focus on the essentials. Now, if you
want to get this media and follow along,
there's a link down in the description.
When you click that link, that'll bring
you to our free community. All you have
to do is join the group. And when you
get to the community, go up to where it
says classroom.
And this media is in our media vault.
This is a huge collection of all kinds
of practice media and footage and
project files and all kinds of cool
stuff. And you can use that to practice
making videos. All the way to the bottom
here is this Star Wars fan film media.
This is what we want. All you have to do
is click this download here button and
you can get everything you need to
follow along. Let's get to it. First
thing you got to do is download Da Vinci
Resolve 21. Right now it's in public
beta, but that is the latest version.
And if you're unfamiliar with Resolve,
well, there's two versions. There's a
free version and a paid version. I'm not
going to go into every single
difference. What you need to know is the
free version is super awesome. You can
use it for commercial work. It doesn't
have a trial period. It doesn't have a
watermark. It's amazing. The paid
version is a 295 onetime fee and it
unlocks even more awesomeness, namely
some AI assisted effects and some fancy
stuff that you may or may not need for
your videos. But whichever version
you're using, download that. And the
first time you open up Resolve, you're
going to have a window like this. This
is what we call our project manager. And
this is kind of like the starting
screen. This is where all your projects
live. It's where you open, save, copy,
export things. You can just go down here
and hit new project. Click on that. Call
it something. I'm just going to call
this demo one. Sure. And hit create. And
that will open up the Resolve interface.
Now, in a second, I'm going to show you
how Resolve works and kind of the big
idea behind like how it's organized and
all that stuff. But just to get you
started as soon as possible, like the
most basic way to bring something into
Resolve is just to find your footage in
your explorer or your Finder window and
just drag this down to this area right
here. And that's going to add it to a
new timeline. And then you can play it
back and you're getting started on your
video. And this timeline here is where
you put clips together. You cut them up,
make them shorter, adjust their order to
create a story. And so you use all of
the different tools in this page as well
as all of the other pages down here to
do specific things and get a little bit
more fancy. And when you're done with
your video and you actually want to show
people, one thing you could do would
just be to go up here to this button
that says quick export. Click on that
and there are some presets that you
could use. So if you're making something
for YouTube, you can select YouTube and
hit export. You can even tick upload
directly right here and you can connect
this with your YouTube channel and
actually upload it right to YouTube from
Resolve, which is pretty cool. But when
you hit export, it'll ask you where you
want to actually put it. I'll just put
it on my desktop and hit save. And there
we are. Timeline 1.mpp4. I can play this
back. And guess what? It's a thing. Yay.
So, if you literally just need
[laughter] to know how to throw videos
into a timeline and export them, that's
how you do it. But the reason you're
using Resolve is probably to get a
little bit more fancy than that, right?
Resolve is a professional level app.
They do color correction, color grading
for Hollywood movies in the same app
that you're using. You can make
absolutely any kind of video in Resolve.
And as crazy as you want to get, it can
handle it. So, let's take a step deeper
and explore how Resolve actually works.
Something to notice about the interface
here is these buttons down below. These
are our pages. And what these do is when
you click on a page, it completely
switches out not just the interface of
the program. It's not like just a preset
workspace. It actually kind of switches
to a different app that's inside of
Resolve. And each one of these pages has
a specific job. So, we've been in the
edit page and its job is to edit videos,
to create an actual timeline. It's like
the hub for where all of your clips go
and how you organize them. just this
part of the app. This kind of does the
job of like Adobe Premiere or Apple
Final Cut or Cap Cut, that kind of
thing. And so Resolve isn't just one
app. It's kind of like several apps in
one. The cut page is kind of a different
approach to editing, although it does a
similar job. It's still putting clips
together on a timeline. It just has a
little bit of a different interface. We
also have a new photo page in Resolve
21, which is meant for actually editing
and doing color grading for your photos.
To the left of the photo page is our
media page. This is where you import
your media and kind of get it organized.
And then to the right of the edit page,
we have our Fusion page, which is where
you make visual effects, kind of like
Photoshop effects for video, and where
you make motion graphics, so animations
and titles and that kind of thing. To
the right of Fusion, we have the color
page, and this is for color grading.
This is the oldest part of Resolve and
definitely still its like biggest draw
because I mean just about every
Hollywood movie these days has been
touched by Resolve at least in the
color. Next to color we have the
Fairlite page and this is like an entire
audio workstation. Of course there's
like no audio in this clip but we'll get
to that. This is how you can get super
deep with your sound design and your
audio mixing for your videos. And then
finally we have the deliver page which
is the way that you would render your
videos properly. So, it's not just a
quick export like I showed you earlier.
It's like being really detailed with the
settings, setting them exactly how you
want, rendering different versions and
different resolutions, and you can
render 20 different things at the same
time. It's very powerful. And so,
Resolve is a absolutely massive beast
when it comes to video creation. It's
like everything that you need in one
place. And right now, if you're watching
this and you're just like, "Oh my gosh,
like I had no idea." [laughter]
You're not alone. One of the biggest
things that we see with people who are
new to Resolve is they go, "Gosh, I just
want to make videos and I feel like I
have to learn a spaceship. Like there
are so many things to concentrate on."
Don't worry, by the end of this video,
you're going to have a much better idea
of what's important and what's not. And
if you need some help on a regular
basis, that's actually what me and my
team do. We have an online community
called Ground Control Film School that
is designed to help you focus on just
what you need to focus on when it comes
to video creation and get rid of all the
other stuff. It includes all of our full
Resolve courses and me and my team
review your work on a regular basis.
It's the best. There's a link in the
description and more about that later.
So, I'm just going to show you the
basics here that you need to really make
some videos cuz the [clears throat] good
news is you don't even need all of these
pages. In fact, you could pretty much
just ignore the cut page, the photo
page, and the media page 90% of the
time. In fact, if it helps, you can even
go up to workspace where it says show
page. You could uncheck the pages you
don't like. So, I could uncheck media,
uncheck photo, uncheck cut. And look at
that. It's already feeling better. But
I'm going to undo that so that nobody
gets confused. So, what do we need
first? Well, if we're going to make a
video, we need some kind of footage to
work with. There are a bunch of ways to
get footage inside of Resolve. One way
we already looked at, which was just
taking some footage and just dragging it
right into that timeline. You could also
rightclick here in this empty space over
here in what we call the media pool, and
go down and say import media. Then you
can just navigate to whatever media you
want and import it. But what I like to
do is just take the media that I want
and drag it into the media pool over
here. Now the media pool is just the
window that holds all of your media.
It's everything that you've actually
imported into the project. It doesn't
mean that your audience is going to see
it. It's kind of just there ready to
use. And what I like to do is just
select my media here. And I'm just going
to select the pieces that you have. Just
going to select these folders. And I can
drag these folders in. And I can either
drag it here into the empty space below
my clips. But what that's going to do is
just put all of the media into my
project. And I actually want to keep the
folders. And so I'm going to drag it
into right here where it says bins right
under there. And what that's going to do
is actually make folders here in the
media pool to keep stuff organized. Now
I have a bin with my audio, a bin with
my footage, a bin with my matte
paintings, a bin with some photos, and
some other goodies. And actually, I'm
going to go ahead and get rid of this
stuff that I grabbed earlier just to
keep us organized. So, now I have five
bins. So, let's talk about the interface
here for just a second. We've been using
the media pool, which is just this kind
of like left-hand window here. That's
the media pool. That's where all our
media for the project lives. Here we
have our source viewer and our timeline
viewer. And down here we have our
timeline. This is really the main
interface of the edit page. What we do
in the source viewer is we can open up a
piece of media here and preview it. Then
we can take it from that preview and
actually put it into the timeline. Once
we have clips in the timeline, we can
actually view what our video is going to
look like in the timeline viewer. Let me
show you what I mean here. I can kind of
mouse over them and I can kind of
preview my footage here in this left
viewer, this source viewer. If I double
click on it, it's going to load it in
the viewer. And so I can move my mouse
around still. And then I can grab this
play head and move this left and right
to preview my clips. And from here, I
can take this clip and move it into the
timeline. Or I can kind of trim it
first. So, one thing I could do would
just be to drag this down to the
timeline. That's going to make a new
timeline, which lives in my media pool.
And then I can see as I scrub through
here, I have my clip showing up in my
timeline viewer. That means it's
actually in the video that I'm making,
and we're not just kind of picking it up
and looking at it. But I could also here
in this viewer, I could trim this to be
shorter. Let's pick a shot that actually
makes sense to trim. And so we have all
this kind of empty space here before
they run. And let's say we want to cut
into this right when they're running.
Well, I can start this clip here just by
clicking this little button right here,
which sets an in. That means like the
start of a clip when you trim it. So we
can set that. And this little gray
selection here moves. And then let's end
it like right here. And so I'll hit this
button, the out. And our little gray
selection moves to be only this big. So
that means that we're just going to take
a part of this clip. And then I can drag
this down into my timeline and it's a
much shorter clip than it would be,
right? We're just using the good part.
All right, we're trimming it before.
Now, we don't have to do it that way.
Once we have a clip in the timeline, we
can actually trim it in the timeline.
And it's kind of the same thing. So,
let's grab this other clip. I'll just
drag it down from the media pool. Now,
we have this big long clip here where
stuff's happening. And let's say I want
it to start right about there. I can
grab the beginning of this clip, just
this little edge right here, and I can
move this this way. And that's going to
make this clip a little bit shorter. So
I can grab this and move it this way
like that. And then the end. Let's trim
that. And we can see there's kind of the
entire clip kind of ghosted with an
outline. So I can see how long the clip
is and how short just my little trim for
that clip is. I can grab the middle of
this and move it around in the timeline.
And I can switch the order of the clips
like this. And this is essentially just
how we build a story in the timeline of
the edit page. We make these clips the
length that we want. We just grab the
parts that we want and we put them in
order with each other. So, if we want to
start with this kind of over-
the-shoulder looking shot where we have
our Jedi here and then our bad guy in
the background and then we cut to a
close-up of our bad guy, we can cut to
this close-up here. So, this one goes
first and then this one and then maybe
they run at each other. If we play this
back, we'll notice that we're on him for
a long time. So, I'm going to trim this
to be a lot shorter. There we go. And
then let's go to the run. And as I move
this over, it kind of snaps to the edges
like that. So now we have these all
together. First clip, second clip, third
clip. And that's the order they're going
to play in. Right? So 1 2
3. Great. Now, at the very beginning of
our timeline, that's way over here. If
we were to leave it like this, we have
this kind of blank space here. And I can
get rid of that blank space in a couple
ways. I could select the blank space and
hit backspace. That's going to move
those over. Or I can select all of these
just with a box select and then drag it
over like that. You don't generally want
blank space in your videos. You just
want to play the clips in order. Okay.
And with just this information, you grab
clips from the media pool. You can
either preview them here, but you
somehow put them into the timeline and
you can trim them in the timeline, move
them around in the timeline to select
the moments that you really want so that
you're building your story in the
timeline. just that will help you make I
mean you need to do that for every
video. So, if you're new to video
editing and that makes sense, oh my
goodness, you are on your way. But now,
let's get picky here for just a second.
You'll notice that this footage is
really kind of gray and desaturated and
nasty looking. All right, it just looks
kind of gray. And yes, [clears throat]
this is on an overcast day, but uh like
there's almost no color to it. It looks
terrible. The reason for this is because
we shot it in log. Log is a special
color mode that certain cameras shoot.
And the point of it is to cram as much
data into your video signal as you can
so that you have a lot of options later
when you're doing color grading. But a
byproduct of that is it comes in looking
bad. Now, there are a lot of ways to fix
this. One of the ways is just to
manually mess with the colors, which
we'll learn a little bit about in a
little while. But the right way to do
it, like the easiest way to do it, the
most highquality way to do it is
actually really easy. And you don't even
need to know what you're doing, and
that's by using color management. This
is a big scary word that everybody gets
gets worried about, but it's so simple.
Let me show you how to do it. Go down to
this little settings cog icon right
here. That's going to bring up our
project settings. Now, there are all
kinds of project settings and specifics
here. You don't need to know most of
this. We're going to go to the fourth
option down where it says color
management. All right. And this very top
part here where it says color space and
transforms. What we got to do is go here
where it says color science and switch
this to Da Vinci Y RGB color managed.
Just like that. And you can totally just
do that and call it good if you want to.
But something that takes two more
seconds and gives you a little bit
higher quality is if you uncheck
automatic color management like this.
And then here where it says color
processing mode instead of SDR rec 709
go down and select HDR Dainci widegamut
intermediate. Okay, that is a big
mouthful. Set these like this and that's
it. I do have super nerdy videos on what
the heck all this means, but literally
if you just set it like this and you
never know why, you're going to be okay.
Like you're going to make awesome
videos. So, just do that. Okay. Then we
hit save. And now our colors still look
gray. H what do we do? Well, this is
kind of the first step in two steps to
fix this. Okay. The first step is go
into color manage mode, which is what we
just did. The second step is tell
Resolve what camera we used to get this
image. To do that, all we have to do is
go over here to the media pool and I'm
just going to box select all of my
media, making sure I'm not selecting the
timeline or this next part won't work.
Just the media. And then I'm going to
right click on any of these. And I'm
going to go down to where it says input
color space. This is where we can select
the type of camera and settings that we
used to shoot our videos, which for us
is Blackmagic Design because we shot on
a Blackmagic camera. And we're going to
select Blackmagic Design Film Gen 5. If
you shot with different footage, if you
shot, say, on a Sony, you're going to
have to pick Sony and pick whichever
settings you used. If you don't know the
settings you used, go and look them up.
Go look in the settings of your camera.
Every camera is different, but most
cameras that shoot log are listed here.
I'm going to go to Blackmagic Design
Film Gen 5 like this. And look what
happens when I select that. Look, our
colors get way, way better. Look at
that. It's still an overcast day. So,
it's not going to look bright and sunny,
but the colors look much, much better.
All right. And that's what we're looking
for when it comes to color management.
We don't want to look at this gray nasty
footage the whole time when we're
editing. And like you saw, we don't
really need to know anything about color
grading just to set a couple menu items.
We're just setting a couple settings.
And that's going to give us a really
decent image to look at while we edit.
And then we'll worry about color grading
and making it look really nice later.
But it's just a lot more fun to look at
an image that looks like this than the
gray nasty one like this. Now, if you're
doing like a gaming video or something
where you don't shoot log, you can skip
that part. This is only for the fancy
cameras that shoot in that kind of gray
desaturated log image. Okay, so we have
our color management set up. We have
some shots in the timeline. As far as
actually working in the timeline, here's
a couple things that you should really
know. One is that a timeline has
multiple tracks. And so, if I wanted to,
I could grab a clip from my media pool
and drag it down here. I could drag it
on this first track, or I can drag it up
above like this on the second track. And
what that's going to do is just show
whatever's on top in my final video. So,
as I play this back, we see just the
clip that's on top. We don't see the
clips under it. So, this can work for
your advantage. Let's say if you want to
try a clip out and see if it works in
your edit without actually getting rid
of stuff or messing with it, you can
just put it on that upper track. The
other thing to mention about this is
while your video you only see one video
at a time regularly for the audio all
the audio is kind of added together. So
you can hear this track as well as this
track and they play together. But for
the video you're only going to see the
top track. Now, there's ways that you
can see multiple tracks and change the
transparency and everything, which we'll
get into in a second, but that's how
things work normally. The other thing
you can do is make your tracks bigger or
smaller just by grabbing this little
edge right here and moving it up or
down. And what I do a lot of the time is
I just make these all small like that
because it plays back a little better.
It's a little bit cleaner looking. And a
lot of the time I'll have the audio
tracks a little bit bigger because one
thing that you can do is you can figure
out kind of where interesting stuff
happens in your clips just by looking at
the audio, looking at the waveform here
because this is where speaking happens.
And so if I just want his line where
he's talking, I don't even have to play
this back. I could trim this to be just
where that audio is and I know that
that's where he's going to be talking.
In fact, a lot of creating your story in
the edit page has a lot more to do with
actually looking at these waveforms and
trimming it to the waveforms than it
does actually looking at the image,
which is kind of crazy, especially when
you're editing something like an
interview or a voice over. You're doing
a lot of looking at the waveforms and
building your story with that audio. And
then a lot of the time, I'll go back and
just see if the video works. But
usually, if the audio works, the video
will work, too. We've already talked
about trimming the edges like this.
Something else you'll find yourself
doing is splitting a clip. I'll just
drag this down so we can just use one
clip here. If I want to split this clip
into two, I can do that a couple ways.
One way would be to grab this razor
blade, select this, and that's going to
turn my cursor into a razor blade. And
then wherever I click, that's going to
split whatever clip I click on. All
right. So, I could come over here and
split this right at the playhead because
it kind of snaps to the playhead. And
now I have two different clips. The
other thing I can do is just split this
at the playhead with a keyboard
shortcut, which by default is control
backslash. So, the backslash that's
right underneath backspace on your
keyboard, control backslash like that.
That's going to cut that. And so, you
can really easily just kind of chop this
up just by hitting control backslash a
lot. And that saves a lot of time
switching in between the tools. Learning
those keyboard shortcuts is essential.
Speaking of keyboard shortcuts, I want
to show you the very best keyboard
shortcut, like the the one that I use
all the time. It will take a clip,
whichever clip you're on, and if you
have, let's say, your playhead right
here, and let's say I want to get rid of
this part. Well, normally what I could
do would be to trim this like this, and
then select all of these clips and then
move them down like that. But there's
actually a keyboard shortcut that will
do all of that at once. And that's
called a ripple trim, which by default
if is control shift left bracket. And
look what it does. It just does all of
that in one fell swoop. Okay. I can also
trim the other side like this. Okay. If
I move this playhead, I can trim this
and move everything down. Control shift
right bracket. Boom. Like that. And
that's going to trim everything up until
the end of the clip. So, control shift
right bracket. Good. Let's say I want
just this little part. Control shift
left bracket like that. So, you can
easily trim stuff in the timeline using
the playhead to kind of aim things and
using keyboard shortcuts to either split
it at the playhead or trim to the right
or the left of it. And let me tell you,
if you are good at that part, you can
get a job editing because that makes
things so so quick. And as much as we
like to think of editing as adding all
kinds of fancy transitions and like
effects and everything, it's mostly
this. It's mostly trimming stuff and
making sure that it's the right length
and that these clips are in the right
order to make your story. And if you can
do that part, the good news is it's that
simple. And the bad news is there's a
lot of it. [laughter] That part is a
little less glorious than you think it
might be. I've been editing videos for
almost 20 years and this is most of it.
Get good at this part. Master the
basics. The better you are at the
basics, the more comfortable you're
going to be in Resolve and the more you
can do the fancy stuff. By default, if I
were to grab a clip by either the video
or the audio, it's going to move both of
these. All right. If I were to trim
either side of this, it's going to move
the audio and the video together. But
you don't have to move them together. By
default, if your video has audio, these
two are linked. But you can unlink them
or move them separately and keep them
linked. You'll notice when I select
this, we have these two little chain
links. That means that the audio and the
video are linked together. I could go
right here where this chain link is, and
I can click it so that it's not white
anymore. It's kind of that gray. And now
when I grab this edge, it doesn't move
both of them. Look at that. The other
thing I could do is keep this linked and
I could hold alt on the keyboard and
move this back and forth. I like doing
it that way because most of the time I
want to move things together, right? I
want to move them both at the same time.
I want to trim them at the same time and
everything. There's only sometimes where
I really want to just adjust the audio
and not the video. That means I can just
hold alt and then maybe drag this out.
And so now I have the audio in this clip
starting before the video. This is what
we call a J cut. Okay? because it kind
of looks like a J. All right. The
opposite of this is an L cut. Okay. So,
if I were to hold Alt and drag this out,
this kind of makes an L. All right.
Here, I'll make it make it a little bit
more L looking. Look, that's an L.
Told you. Okay, this one's a J. J L. And
you use these to kind of soften your
edits. What I mean by that is when you
cut from one clip to another, especially
if they sound different, it can kind of
be a harsh transition. For instance, let
me just kind of cut in between this. And
when I play this, it'll be a pretty
harsh transition.
>> Okay. But if I take this audio and I
bring the audio in first before we cut
to the video, I can just hold alt and
grab this. And I can trim both of these
at the same time, which is called a
roll. So I'm trimming this clip and this
clip at the same time. And I roll this
here. So, we have his line coming in
before that video. Look at how good this
feels.
>> I'm here for the droid.
>> Yeah. See, it feels like it softens it.
It kind of brings you in with the audio
and then the video hits. That's the kind
of thing that actually happens a lot
more in professional edits. What happens
sometimes is you'll have an edit like
this
>> and you're like, well, I don't want that
to feel so sudden. And so, there'll be a
temptation to kind of crossfade them.
All right, which by the way you can do
if you select in between these clips
like this, this little green selection.
I'm just clicking it once. I can
rightclick and I can say add cross
dissolve. It doesn't really matter which
one I pick. I'll pick 12. And that's
going to fade these clips together like
this. So check this out.
>> It's a crossfade.
>> All right.
>> And it does soften it. It doesn't feel
as sudden, but it also kind of feels
weird. Really, the only time you want a
fade like this for the most part is if
there's a big passage of time. But if
you're just trying to soften that edit,
don't fade it just to soften it, cuz it
sends the wrong message. If we want to
soften that edit, we just do something
like a J cut.
>> Droid.
>> See, even that feels better.
>> I'm here for the droid.
>> Yeah, that's much better. Okay, so a
couple other things in the edit page.
When you have a clip selected, you can
adjust kind of the details, the
properties of the clip by going over to
the inspector. That's this button right
here. You can open this up. And I'll
click on this little downy button thing
here [laughter] to extend this to be the
full height of the screen. And this is
just a list kind of of the properties of
the clip that we have selected. And so
with this clip selected, I can go up
here to the transform controls and I can
put my mouse here and just kind of click
and drag to the right to make this zoom
in. Same thing for the position. I can
kind of move this around rotation. And I
can reset each control with these little
reset buttons. Or I can reset the whole
group of controls with this little
circle arrow plus button like that. So
really anything that you want to do to
this specific clip when you have it
selected the properties are opened up in
the inspector. And this is something
that is common throughout Resolve, not
just the edit page. The same thing
happens in Fairlite and in Fusion. It's
especially important in Fusion. But if
you want to do something like crop this
clip, like cut this edge off, you do
this by clicking on cropping. And that
twirls down this little section here.
And I can crop this like that. And
there's all kinds of goodies to play
around with here. One of them that I
really like is the dynamic zoom. So,
I'll select this clip right here, which
is just people running at each other.
And you'll notice there's no zoom at
all. But if I click on dynamic zoom,
this will automatically zoom this in
over
the length of the clip. And so, if the
clip is shorter, it zooms it in faster.
And if it's longer, it zooms it slower.
So, this is especially good for things
like slideshows where you want to have a
little bit of movement on all of your
images. You can select all of your
images and then just tick on dynamic
zoom and each one will zoom which is
really really helpful. But the essential
concept here is when you select
something down here in the timeline that
its properties show up here in the
inspector. That's how you adjust its
details. Now, the same thing happens
when we add an effect. So, let's go to
this shot right here and we can add an
effect to this by going up here to right
next to our media pool. we have this
little button that says effects. I can
click on this. That's going to switch
this panel to be effects. I'll move my
camera down here so we can actually see
it. And in this effect browser, we have
all kinds of different effects, all
kinds of goodies. So, if I want to put a
blur on this, let's say, I can just drag
this down onto the clip like this. When
it turns white, I'll let go. And that's
going to add that radial blur to this
clip. And then when I have the clip
selected here in the effects tab, I can
adjust the properties of the effect.
because I have the clip selected and I
have the effects selected here. And now
I can change how this works. Isn't that
cool? Maybe I'll change the center
position a little bit. Get crazy. And I
can easily turn this on and off by
clicking this little on and off switch.
Nice way to kind of preview this and
click the garbage can to get rid of it.
There we go. And there are all kinds of
effects. We don't have time to go over
all the effects, but there's a lot. All
right. In the free version, there's
quite a bit. And in the paid version,
there's even more. And these aren't just
effects that you can drop onto the
clips. Up here we have our titles and
our generators. So I can twirl down
titles. And here we have a whole bunch
of titles that we can use for various
reasons. Some of them have animation.
And you can mouse over these to kind of
see a preview of the animation.
That's nice. And once you find one you
like, you can just drag it to the
timeline just like a clip. And that
shows up here in the timeline. Again,
you select this to bring up its
properties in the inspector. And you can
adjust the text and everything. Let's
actually look at this. So, we'll say,
you know, Star Wars. You can change the
font. For instance, we could use a Star
Warsy font. Haha. [laughter] Of course,
the animation is a little different than
you might do for Star Wars, but that's
how you adjust the details of your
titles as you click on them and open
them up here in the inspector. This is
kind of a fancier title, but they have
basic titles here at the top. So, I
could just grab this normal text. Grab
this and plug that in there. And we can
adjust what it says and the font. There
we go. And you have all of your controls
for like your font and your tracking and
your spacing and all of that. You can
add a stroke to the font if you want to.
You can add a drop shadow. You just have
to click and drag this offset and that
will kind of activate it like that. You
can make a background. I'll turn off the
drop shadow and push up the height of
the background. That'll make a little
shape behind it. So, there are a lot of
tools that you can adjust for your title
just within this one text title. Isn't
that nuts? And this is one of several
basic ones, which aren't even as crazy
as the Fusion titles, which there's a
ton. There's a ton of them. But that's
how you add text. You can just grab some
text, throw it on there, and you trim
this and move it around just like you
would a piece of media in the timeline.
But we're going to keep moving, and I'm
going to show you some essentials of the
other pages as well. And we're going to
start in Fusion. The first thing I'll do
is just make sure my playhead is over a
certain shot. So, how about this one?
And then I'm just going to click on the
fusion page. What that's going to do is
switch over to the fusion page and it's
going to open the shot that I was over
in the timeline in Fusion. So, here we
go. Now, we're working on this shot.
Now, just as kind of a basic concept of
how Fusion works. When you open up a
shot like this, you're working on that
shot in the timeline, but with your
Fusion tools. Okay. So, let me do
something fusiony to this real quick.
And then I'll kind of explain what we're
doing here in a minute.
I'll just grab some clouds and put it
over here. So, this is nice and cloudy.
Now, I'm going to switch back over to
the edit page, and we'll see on the edit
page that we still have our shot really
cloudy. So, as I play this back, we have
the clouds over this shot that we're
actually adding in Fusion. Now, this is
something that's really important
because all of the clips live here in
the timeline, and they all have certain
properties, right, that live in the
inspector, but they also can be adjusted
by Fusion and color, but they always
live here in the timeline. So, we'll get
to color in a few minutes, but for
Fusion, all we have to do is just be
over this clip and then switch over to
Fusion. And now we're editing that clip
itself inside of the timeline. Now, it's
not actually making changes to the
original clip at all. It's kind of like
applying a effect to it in the timeline,
but the effect lives in Fusion. Once you
play with it a little bit, you kind of
get the idea. And this is really one
kind of major category of stuff that
Fusion can do, which is adjust a shot
from your timeline and you can do visual
effects to it. That's stuff like adding
fog and doing things that you would do
in Photoshop and adding fire and
explosions and duplicating people and
adding 3D and stuff like that. That kind
of stuff is called visual effects. So,
it's kind of changing your footage. The
other thing that Fusion can do is make
titles and animations and that kind of
thing. We'll get to that in a few
minutes. For now, let's look at a couple
of basics on how Fusion is set up and
what the heck Fusion is and what it does
because this is the most powerful page
of Resolve. And it's also the most
intimidating and confusing. Here's the
essentials. If you're going to do visual
effects, you open up a clip in Fusion
from your timeline, which like we've
done here. Just over the clip, switch it
over to Fusion. That brings it into the
Fusion interface, which is made up of a
couple things. We have the viewers,
which are here. We have the actual time
ruler. That's where you can click and
drag to move back and forth in time.
It's like your playhead. And we have the
playback controls. Here we have our
toolbar where we can grab different
tools and use them in the node graph.
And then we have the node graph itself.
This is like the breadand butter of
Fusion. This is where 90% of the work
happens. What we're doing down here is
we're building a flowchart that we run
our image through. And by default, the
starting point of this flowchart is we
have the original footage, the OG
footage, and then we have what's
rendered. Okay, it's what's being put
into the timeline. Okay, let's just say
render to timeline. And each one of
these boxes is called a node. And these
nodes flow into each other. So, we're
starting with this node and then it
flows over to this node. And you can
always kind of read this in a linear
way. We're grabbing our original
footage. Then we're doing nothing to it
and then we're rendering it to the
timeline. That's why it looks normal
like this. But what we can do along this
line is we can run it through other
nodes that change the image. So for
instance, if we wanted to make this
really blurry, we could run it through a
blur node. We can grab a blur node by
clicking and dragging this little
teardrop down here like this. So, I can
grab it, drag it down. That's going to
make a blur node. And then we can take
this original node. I'm just going to
click on this line to get rid of it. And
then I can take this little output, this
gray output, and plug that into the
yellow input like this. And this gray
output, and plug this into the yellow
input like this. And this makes this
image slightly blurry. It's a little bit
hard to see on the recording. So, I'm
going to select the blur node and go up
here to blur size and push that up.
Now, that should be familiar because I'm
selecting something down here and its
properties show up in the inspector and
I adjust it, right? Just like we would
adjust an effect in the edit page. So,
now step one is we grab our original
footage. Step two is we blur it. And
step three, we put it back on the
timeline. So, if I switch over to the
edit page, we have our blurry footage on
the timeline. Okay. Now, something just
to drive home here. If I didn't have
this connected and I just had my
original footage connected to my media
out like this, this would not be blurry.
Just putting one of these nodes down
here in this space doesn't affect
anything. It only affects stuff when you
link them up. Okay, we're building a
flowchart and unless it flows through
one of the nodes, it's not going to
actually do anything. Now, if we were to
go up to the effects panel and twirl
this down, we could see under tools all
of the different nodes that are
available in Fusion. And it's a lot.
It's over 300 nodes. It's a lot of
nodes. And if you're just learning
Fusion, you're probably like, "Dude,
[laughter]
that's way too many. How am I ever going
to know all these nodes? What am I going
to do?" Oh, relax.
You don't need to know all of the nodes.
In fact, you only need to know just a
few. And to simplify this even more, you
really only need to know four different
kinds of nodes. There's really only four
kind of categories of nodes. And every
node within each category really kind of
acts the same way. The first category
would be called an image node. So that's
like this node right here. This is a
starting point. Okay? It's a raw
ingredient, an image of some kind. So
this is our original footage. Okay? We
could also generate an image like with
this background node. If I grab this
down, I could say make a red background.
And if I plug this into the media out,
look what happens. It becomes a red
background because I'm generating a red
image with that node. Okay? And I'm just
plugging this into the media out, which
just renders it to the timeline. Same
thing I could do with a text node. This
right here, grab that down. We'll say
text. I can plug this output into the
media out and look we have text to the
screen. It's rendering that text and
making an image. Okay, so these are all
image nodes. Okay, image image nodes.
The next kind of node we've already
used, it's an effect node. So this node
right here, this blur node, this is an
effect node. The reason I know it's an
effect node is because it changes an
image. All right. Just like if you apply
a blur to a clip on the edit page, you
actually just run an image through an
effect like this. Okay? Because an
effect only changes an image that runs
through it like this. So we have a
blurry original image. If I take this
text and I plug this in, we have blurry
text. If I have this background and we
plug this in, we have a blurry
background, but you can't really tell.
[laughter]
So that blur is affecting things that go
through it. Now, there are a few
different effects. Like a color
correction effect would do the same
thing. So, let's go through this color
corrector effect. And I'll just plug
that through and we'll change this
color. That's only going to affect
things that go through the color
corrector effect. Same thing with like
brightness and contrast, right? Kind of
a similar thing. Boom. Can change this
contrast. Great. That only affects
things that go through it. So these are
all effect nodes. Effect nodes affect
things that go through it. Effects
nodes. One interesting effect node is a
transform. That's this one right here.
If I grab this down, this is a
transform. And what this does is this
changes an image. And so I'll push this
through here. But it doesn't change it
like it doesn't change the pixels
necessarily. It moves the image around.
So, if I select transform and adjust the
size, that's going to resize my image
and I can rotate it and everything just
like the controls for the clips here in
the edit page. If I select a clip here,
just like these transform controls right
here, these are controls that are kind
of isolated just in this node. And so,
you can decide to move something just by
putting it through that node. You're
applying a transformation to it and it's
technically an effect. The third kind of
node is a merge node. So a merge node
are these two nodes right here. I'll
just grab this first one and drag this
down. What a merge node does is it puts
one image over another image. So if I
throw this blur into merge one and I
take the output of merge one and put
that into media out one, we have our
blurry Star Wars background, which makes
sense because that's what's hooked up,
right? But if I had this text, I could
put this text into the green input of
the merge like this. Look what happens.
Now we have text over that background.
So that's how you stack things in
Fusion. You don't have layers. You only
have nodes that put images over other
images. And it's actually kind of the
same idea as having a layer. It's just
laid out in a different interface. When
I first started with Fusion, I thought
this was the dumbest thing. [laughter]
But it's actually really cool because
you can have an image that is put in
multiple different places. is you could
put this into 10 different merges in 10
different places in your composition and
you're just reusing that one image.
Whereas with layers, if you have layer 1
and then you put something in layer 2,
that's where it lives in the layer stack
and it can only live in one place. But
that's how we put an image over another
image. All right, with this merge node
and with the regular merge, you can only
have a foreground and a background. And
so if you want to put more stuff in
front, so if I want to have some clouds
in front, I can grab this generator
here, this fast noise, and I can drag in
a merge. And I'll just drag this onto
the line where it turns blue and yellow,
and let go. That'll connect that. And
then I'll take the output from this, and
put that into the green. And now I have
the clouds over the text, which is over
the background. And I can adjust the
transparency of the layers of the
foreground layer by selecting this merge
and adjusting blend like this. Now I can
blend that foreground down if I want to.
I could select this one and blend that
foreground down. Adjust the opacity of
that text. And this is how you build
things in Fusion. The last category of
node is a mask. Now, this is cool. All
right, let's get rid of a couple of
these just to make this a little bit
easier to understand.
Okay, we have our guy, we have our text.
Let's say I want to put our text behind
our guy. We can do this with a mask.
these little nodes right here. I can
grab maybe this third one and drag it
down. And this is called a polygon mask.
It's a way to draw with the pen tool on
the screen. And you can select an area
on screen that you want to include or
not include in various different ways.
With my polygon, I'm going to go over
here and just draw around my guy a
little bit. Now, I'll just do this
really quick so that we can move on. And
if I were just to put this mask into the
media out, we can see it's kind of
making a black and white image here.
I'll connect this again. I can take this
polygon and I can plug this into the
blue input of that merge. And look what
happens when I do that. It keeps that
text only within that mask. And so from
there, I can select this mask and go and
say invert.
And that will mask everything but the
guy, right? And so we can adjust this
and kind of play around and make sure it
looks really good. So we have our text
behind our guy. Isn't that cool? And so
that's how you put things behind people
is with masks. And there are so many
different kinds of masks and there's AI
assisted masks now and all kinds of
stuff. But the basics are that you have
some kind of node that controls the
transparency of another node. So this
polygon mask controls where this merge
does its job. All right. You can also
apply a mask to an image like this. If I
take this output, plug this into the
blue input of our Star Wars guy. Check
this out. Now, it's actually cutting him
out, which may or may not be what you
want. The great thing is you are in
control, complete control of what
happens to your image in this little
pipeline. Some people love this and some
people don't. If you're looking at this
and you're a little bit resistant, I
would encourage you to give it a chance.
Get in and play because it is really
fun. I have so [snorts] many videos on
Fusion and if you're willing to learn
nodes and jump in and get messy, it's a
really good time. Okay, so let's look at
some color essentials. Let's throw this
down here and just switch to the color
page. Now, the layout of the color page
is one of those really intimidating
things. If you're brand new to Resolve,
it probably looks like you're sitting at
the helm of a spaceship. And that's
really common. But I'm going to simplify
everything for you right now. When we
switch to the color page, what we're
doing is we're opening the same timeline
that we're working on in the edit page.
So, this timeline right here is just
being worked on in the color page. In
fact, you can see a little preview of
the timeline kind of here in the middle.
And we can move our playhead back and
forth to navigate our timeline. And
there's really just a couple of sections
here in the interface. There's the
viewer, obviously. There's the nodes
over here. We'll get to those later. I'm
going to close this gallery here for a
minute. In the middle here, we have a
way to just navigate our timeline or in
between different clips. So, I can
select whichever clip I want to color
grade just by clicking on the thumbnail
there. And that goes to that clip in my
timeline instantly. And when I have this
clip selected, that is the image that
I'm working on. That's the clip that I
am going to color grade. All of this
stuff down here, everything here, these
are just controls for actually changing
that image. So, you can kind of think of
this as just like one big group of
stuff. And we call this the pallets. I
always forget if that word has two L's
or two T's. If it's wrong, forgive me.
But long story short, when you grab this
control or this control or this control
or this control, all of those are
actually affecting just this clip. And
you can see what's happening in this
clip in the viewer. And so if I were to
grab one of these color wheels, which
we'll talk about in a second, and grab
this little dot and push this this way
like this,
that's going to make this clip pink. And
we're going to see that it's pink up
here in the viewer. And if you're brand
new to color, it does not have to get
lots more complicated than that. What we
do in the color page is just select a
clip that we want to adjust and then we
use whatever control we want down here
to adjust it. In fact, we can make this
even a little bit more simple by
toggling some of our panels off and on.
So, I'll toggle off nodes, toggle off
timeline, toggle off clips. So, we're
just looking at our image and our
controls down here. In these pallets, we
have all kinds of little controls. And
these buttons right here actually switch
out the controls. So as I switch to
different buttons, this switches to
different kinds of pallets. And each
pallet, some of them have sub pallets.
Like I mean [laughter] like all these
right here, there's more different kinds
of controls. And so there's so much to
explore here in the color page, which
some people love and some people it
stresses them the heck out. For right
now, at first, we're just going to
ignore all of this and we're going to
ignore all of this stuff and we're just
going to focus on this panel right here.
This is called our primary color wheels.
And there's a lot of controls here, too.
But the good news is you really only
need to know a couple of them to do so
much color stuff. One of the big things
you'll do in color grading is make a
image brighter or darker. And you can do
that with these little sliders down
here. Now, why are there four of them?
Well, these are different controls for
the different ranges of brightness in
the image. Here's what that means. This
one on the right under offset, if I were
to grab this and pull this to the right,
it's going to make everything brighter.
I can reset it by clicking any of these
little reset buttons here. If I were to
take this to the left, it's going to
make it darker like this. I'm just
grabbing and dragging it to the left.
that makes the whole image darker. So
offset controls the whole image. But
lift, gamma, and gain, those control the
darkest parts, the midtones, and the
lightest parts of the image. So if I
were to grab this same control here in
the gain, and I were to push this to the
right, that's going to make the brighter
parts brighter. If I push it to the
left, that's going to make the brighter
parts darker.
Let's say I want to make the shadows a
lot brighter. I can take this lift and
take this to the right and that's going
to make the darker parts of my image
lighter, which is going to make the
whole image lighter, but it's mostly
going to affect the darker parts. And
then same thing here in the gamma. If I
were to move this up or down, it makes
the midtones darker or brighter. And so
you can use a combination of these
sliders to affect the brightness of your
image as well as the contrast. That's
the difference between the bright and
the dark parts. So, I could take this
gain and push this to the right and the
lift and push it to the left. And look
what happens. As I push this to the
right, it makes the brighter parts
brighter. And as I take the lift and
push it to the left, it makes the darker
parts darker, which means that we get
more contrast. If I hit shift D, that's
going to disable my color grade. And I
can toggle that off and on to see the
difference. So, here's before those two
adjustments that I made, and here's
after. So, I'm increasing that contrast.
I'm making the darker parts darker and
the brighter parts brighter. But we can
adjust more than just the brightnesses
of the image. We can also adjust what
color things are. And we can do this in
the color wheels. And these are split up
just like the sliders are. So if I take
this offset and push this a little bit
blue, it makes everything a little more
blue. If I take and push it to the
green, it makes it green and so on. But
I can also do this in the lift, gamma,
or gain to affect the different tones in
the image. So for instance, I could take
my gain and push that a little bit
warmer and it's going to make the
brighter parts warmer. I could take my
lift and push that a little bit cooler
and that's going to make the darker
parts cooler. Now again, it's going to
affect the whole image. It's just
stronger in the darker parts. And so as
you kind of push and pull this, you can
get all kinds of interesting looks by
pushing the gain one way and the lift
another way.
So just knowing these sliders and the
color wheels, you have a lot of control
over your image. But we also have these
controls here on the top and bottom of
the color wheels. And these we can click
and drag to the left or right right here
on the number. And as I grab and pull
these to the right, various things
happen. So as I grab contrast, I can add
a little bit of contrast just with one
slider. I can grab this pivot and move
that back and forth. And that adjusts
the midpoint of the contrast. So it kind
of decides if there's more things that
are considered light or more things that
are considered dark. So contrast and
pivot, they kind of work together. You
can double click on any of these to
reset them. And it's a good idea to just
grab these and explore. The great thing
about the color page and really Resolve
in general is it's really hard to mess
something up. You very rarely do
something that you can't undo. So, I
mean, if I make this really pink and
then push some contrast in it and change
the pivot around and mess with the tint
and, you know, desaturate it and all
this stuff, I can make this look
horrible. But all I have to do is click
this little button right here and look,
boop, it's back to where it was. It's no
big deal. There's no stress here. So,
get in here and play around. So, let me
just show you the essential things that
I look at when I'm adjusting an image.
The first thing I pay attention to is,
okay, how's the brightness of the image?
How does it feel? I'm looking at this
and it feels it feels good. I don't
think it's overly bright or dark. It's
probably fine. One thing that it could
definitely take is a little more
contrast because I want these darker
parts to be a little bit darker and the
brighter parts to be a little bit
brighter. And so I can adjust that
however I want. I can take the gain
master wheel to the right and the lift
master wheel to the left or I can just
take this contrast and take that to the
right. So I'll maybe I'll do that. I'll
push that contrast until I have a little
bit more contrast there and I like it a
little better. Then sometimes I'll grab
the pivot and move it around to see if I
like it a little brighter, a little
darker, something like that. And then
I'll go back to the image and I'll look
at it and say, "Okay, the contrast looks
a little better. What about just the
colors? Does it feel like the colors are
saturated enough? Like the colors are
bright enough and strong enough?" Well,
I say maybe maybe we could put a little
bit into that. So I could take this
saturation and push this to the right.
Take this and push that in. And now
we're getting that nice green grass
there. Now, this is a little bit little
bit crazy maybe, but now we have really
nice bright colors. And remember, we can
always grab this playhead and just move
this back and forth to scrub through our
footage. Now we have a little bit of
skin tone there, so we have an idea of
what skin tones look like. That's
looking a lot better. Remember, you can
always hit shift D, disable your color
grade. That's the same thing as going up
here to this little rainbow sparkle
button and clicking this. You can see
before and after. Yeah, we're making a
big difference here with just a couple
of sliders. All I did was grab this
contrast, push this to the right, adjust
the pivot a little bit, and then I took
the saturation up a little bit. Like
that. That's I really touched it three
times. And look at that difference.
Isn't that crazy? That's the power of
the color page. This is three little
adjustments on just one of these
palettes, which is just one of the many,
many palettes in the color page. It's
crazy. This is why we have an essentials
video like this, so you don't get lost.
I think I'll take that saturation down a
little bit. I can also adjust the
temperature and the tint. So, I can
maybe push this temperature a little bit
cooler. I can change the tint around.
And I'm just citing how I want this clip
to feel. Do I want it to feel bright and
happy or exciting? No. This is like a,
you know, a duel to the death. So, we're
not probably going to do that. So, we're
going to keep it kind of cool and
somber. And as far as the essentials of
adjusting the color in your videos, this
is really like the big thing when it
comes to adjusting a clip. And like I
said, there are a lot of other tools
that you can use for various reasons,
but this is the biggest bang for your
buck, just staying in these primary
color wheels. Man, you can do so much
with these. And really, what I like to
do is I like to look at the image and
say, what does this need? Is it too dark
or too bright? I feel like this is maybe
just a touch dark. So, I could take this
gain and just push that to the right a
little bit. What about the saturation? I
can change the saturation and push this
to the right to make it more saturated
or to the left to make it less
saturated. I could change the
temperature and the tint to really give
this a little bit of a different feel.
But doing color grading is really a lot
more than just adjusting one image. If
you think about this, we're actually
working on a sequence, right? So,
there's multiple different shots in this
timeline, and we want to make sure that
not only does each image look good, but
that they match together and that they
all work as one project. So, I'll just
reset my
layout here. And so, we have five
different shots here, and we want to
make sure that they all work together.
And this is really where workflow comes
in because you could certainly just
switch to this next shot, you know, and
play around with it and change the
temperature and all of that stuff and
use the color tools that we've learned
here in the primary color wheels. But
then when you switch in between them,
you're like, "Okay, well, do those
match? Okay, well maybe this one needs
to be a little bit darker and then what
about this one? And how do we change
that?" And it gets overwhelming really
quickly. And so I'm going to show you a
really easy way to get your shots so
they match. And you don't even have to
be a professional colorist. Okay. The
first thing I'm going to do is hold
shift and select all of these clips. And
then I'm going to rightclick here in
this empty space and say reset all
grades and nodes. That's just going to
reset everything. All I have is my color
management on which we set up earlier.
And I'm also going to close my timeline
just so I have a little bit more room
here in the interface. And there's
really kind of like three big main parts
to this color workflow that's going to
be so easy. We're going to group all of
our shots. We're going to pick an
example shot to compare everything to.
And then we're going to use nodes in a
really smart way. So, the first thing
I'm going to do is just shift select all
of my shots here and then rightclick and
select add into a new group. And we'll
call this look. L O K. Like that. All
right. This is going to add all these
shots to a group. And for now, nothing's
really going to change. So, if I make
this shot pink, it just changes the shot
pink like normal. But there is a little
difference here. You'll notice down
below each of these shots is a chain
link icon. That means that all of these
are in the same group. And when we have
shots in a group, we can actually make a
color adjustment to all the shots
together. To do that, I'm going to go up
here to where it says clip above my
nodes. And I'm going to twirl this down
and select group post clip. I'll select
that. That's going to turn this node
yellow, which means that we're in group
post clip mode. And now any adjustment
that I make with these nodes up like
this. If I push this pink, look at that.
It changes all of them to pink. So, this
is really great because I can make a
common adjustment that all of the clips
are going to need without having to redo
work on every single clip. So, I'll
right click here and say reset all
grades and nodes. That's kind of the
first part is I'm putting everything
into a group. Next, I'm going to pick a
shot that I really like that also has
some common elements between the other
shots. So, for instance, this shot, shot
four, we have the guy in the black robe,
the guy in the brown robe, we have the
lightsabers, we have the foliage. Those
things exist in our other shots, too.
Even this first shot, we have the
foliage and the guy in the brown robe.
Same thing here. Guy in the black robe
here. And then our last shot, we have
all of those same elements. So, shot
four is actually a really great shot to
kind of make some moviewide decisions.
And again, we don't have to over
complicate this. I can look at this shot
and go, "Okay, what does this need?" I
feel like it needs maybe a little more
contrast. So, I'll take the contrast
slider and push it to the right like
this. Just add a little more contrast.
Maybe darken this down a little bit.
I'll take the gamma and push it down.
Make it a little bit more dramatic.
Maybe I'll take the saturation down just
a touch. Kind of desaturate this. Maybe
I'll play around with the temperature.
Maybe make that a little bit more blue.
Change that tint. Sure. Something like
that. Maybe I want a little more
contrast in here. There we go. Yeah,
something like that. So, here's our
image now. And here's where it was
before. So, it doesn't even look like we
did a whole lot until you turn this off
and on. We get these nice rich tones in
the brown. We have these nice dark
blacks here without putting too strong
of a look on it. We still have detail in
the dark parts, but the black parts are
black. Yeah, I think that works really
nice. We get a little bit more color
from our foliage. Feels good. So, let's
say that we really like how this looks.
Something I can do is just right click
on this viewer and I'll select grab
still. What that's going to do is
actually save this color grade into a
little preset over here called a still.
And it's going to combine it with an
actual still image that you can use and
you can export as a image if you want
to. But what we're going to use it for
is to compare our other shots to. Now,
check this out. This is this is the
power. Okay, let's switch over to shot
five real quick. And then I'm going to
go up to my still, right click, and say
play still. What that's going to do is
give me a split screen of these two
shots so that I can compare them really,
really easily. So, we have our example
shot set the way that we want. And now
what we're going to do is just look at
the difference between these shots and
adjust this shot to match the still.
When we do that, we're going to use
nodes in a very specific way. Right now,
remember, we're still in the group post
clip nodes, which means that anything
that we do here, say if I make this
pink, that's going to happen to all of
the shots, which is actually not what I
want right now. I want to go back to
adjusting the individual shots so that I
can fix the differences in between them
and they all match. So, let me get rid
of this offset here. I'll just click on
this reset button, and I'm going to
switch back over from group post clip
nodes back to clip nodes. So, again, if
I make this pink, that's only going to
affect this shot. I can right click and
reset. So now I'm just going to adjust
this clip to match our still, which I
can do in the primary color wheels. But
something to mention, when I adjust
something in the primary color wheels or
anything down here, that adjustment
actually lives inside of this node right
here. Okay? Whichever node that I have
selected, you can think of this just as
like a box that contains all of these
color adjustments that I'm making. And
what's neat about this is I can make
another node. So I could just rightclick
and say add node, add serial. This is
just a node that goes in a series. So we
do this one first and then this one
second. And I can select this node and
this will be another group of
corrections. And so if I take this
offset back more towards green, I can
just about neutralize this image because
I'm making it pink and then I'm adding
green to it, which kind of cancels it
out. Now, I could have done both of
those things in one node, but I have the
option to split them up if I want to.
Now, why would you split them up? The
big reason is just organization. You can
kind of think of this as steps. So, I
could right click on this and say node
label. And we'll call this uh, you know,
exposure.
And I'll adjust the exposure for this
clip just by maybe by grabbing this
offset and pushing it up to match this
clip. And that's my exposure adjustment.
Now, I could adjust the temperature and
the tint and the saturation and 100
other things right here. And those
adjustments would live in this node, and
there's nothing wrong with doing that,
but to keep myself really organized, I'm
actually going to make another node.
Right click, add node, add serial. You
can also hit alt s. And with this node
selected, I'm going to be selective
about the adjustments that I make. I'm
going to rightclick and say node label.
And we'll call this saturation. Okay.
So, let's say I want to adjust some
saturation here. I'm just going to
select this and then grab my saturation
and I can adjust that and move that
around to be just right. And what's nice
about this is if I want to see what this
image looks like without the exposure
adjustment, I can click on this node
number to turn it off and on. Same thing
for saturation. And I can kind of look
at the different steps that I'm taking
in a modular way and turn one on or off.
And so if I want to do some kind of
experiment, let's say I can hit Alt S
and add another node. And we'll call
this, you know, contrast. And I can
crank up this contrast and see if I like
it and play around. And then I'm not
messing up anything else because I can
always just disable this node or even
delete it if I don't like what I did.
So, it's a really smart modular way to
work. Now, what's like next level here?
What's like the best way to do this is
to set up your nodes not just to be
modular, but to be like a to-do list for
yourself. So, what I like to do is
something I like to call the ecto
method. All right, I'm going to reset
our all grades and nodes. And I'm going
to add a couple of different nodes here.
I'll hit alt s and make four nodes. And
I'm going to label each one. This one's
going to be E, C, T, O.
It's just easy to remember, like Ecto
from the Ghostbusters, right? E stands
for exposure, C is contrast, T is for
temperature and saturation, O is for
other stuff. And what we can do is
select all of our clips like this. And
we can copy these nodes into all of our
clips. Even though these are blank
nodes, they're not doing anything right
now. I could middle button mouse click
or I could right click on shot 5 and say
apply grade. And now if I go to these
different clips, we see those ectto
nodes throughout here. Okay, this looks
crazy and fancy, but it's really not.
All this is is four blank nodes where
nothing is going on, just labeled ectto
here. Now, here's where it gets awesome.
So, I'll switch over to shot five. And
remember, we have our split screen here.
Now, I'm just going to go through this
like a to-do list. E for exposure. Is
the exposure right? Okay, I'm going to
maybe change my offset and push that up
and adjust the exposure to be better.
And I'll kind of go in between this.
Okay, maybe play around. See if I can
adjust the exposure there. Cool. Now,
let's look at the contrast. Is the
contrast right? I feel like the contrast
is maybe a little much in this shot. So,
maybe I'll take the contrast down a
little bit. Okay. Temperature. Is the
temperature the same? Let's grab the
temperature and move that back and
forth.
I feel like it's pretty good. And then O
for other stuff. Now, actually, this
exposure, I feel like we could maybe
push this up a touch. Yeah, I feel like
that's going to work a little bit
better. Now, these match a lot better
than they were. Maybe this temperature.
I'll take the saturation down a little
bit. There we go. That's going to fix
this.
Maybe even more. Something like that.
Now, if we're getting to the point where
I can't quite tell the difference in
between these, maybe we'll take this
temperature a little bit more blue.
Something like that. That's when these
are going to match pretty well. I can
select all of these and hit control D
for disable. Look at the difference that
we're making in between these shots.
It's just a bunch of little tweaks that
really make these match a little bit
better. So, the question is, how do you
match all of your shots to work
together? Well, you just compare them
all to your example shot. So, shot
three. Does this compare with our
example? Actually, this looks pretty
good. I'd say don't need to do a whole
lot to it. And something important is
just to not overthink it. If it feels
like it works, just move on. It's okay.
Shot two. Now, this is obviously way too
dark. Okay. So, let's fix the biggest
thing first. The exposure. All right.
Let's take this and I'll push this
offset up. We want this to be much, much
brighter. That's working a lot better.
What about the contrast? Maybe you could
take this contrast down a touch. The
temperature and saturation. I feel like
that works a lot better.
Good. So, those are going to match a lot
better than they were. Maybe could go
just a little warm. Much much better.
I'm looking at the browns. Do the browns
match? Do the greens match? Do this
foliage back here match? Does it feel
like it lives in the same world? Yes.
Switch back over to shot one. And I'll
move this to a good place. And again.
Okay. What needs to change here? Let's
take the exposure. Push that exposure
up. Ooh, that's going to fix a lot of
stuff. Ooh, that's much better. Let's
just take that offset up. Oh, yeah.
So good. Much better. Much much better.
Play with this contrast. Maybe could add
a little contrast to it. Temperature.
Let's maybe take the saturation down a
little bit.
That looks pretty good. Much better. And
now that we've gone through each of
those shots and we had a little to-do
list for each of the shots. Now, if I
turn off this split screen, which is
just right here, this little button.
Turn this off. If I click through this,
these should all match pretty well. And
yeah, I don't think there's anything.
This one's maybe just a little bit
yellow. So maybe we'll take this
temperature just a little bit cooler and
just flip in between them. You should be
able to flip to any shot and they should
all feel like they live in the same
world. And if that's true, then they're
going to match pretty well. See how easy
that was to match that? It's all about
having a good color workflow. But that's
really what's going to get you started
in the color page. It's not all about
learning a specific tool. It's more of
the technique. It's more of the workflow
of adjusting one image, which you can do
with the color wheels or any other tool
that you want. putting these all in a
group and doing the the kind of big work
here first because remember we're making
a lot of adjustments to all of these
shots all together in the group. And
then under that group grade, we're also
adjusting the clips. I have a lot of
videos and training on this kind of
workflow. It's the best workflow, man.
And there's so much to go over with the
color page. I mean, reading scopes and
all the fancy things that you can do
with masks and selecting certain colors
and everything, but this is the basics.
Get good at this first because that's
what's really going to help your videos.
Nobody's going to care if you have a
vignette on this shot if your shots
don't match. All right, that's the
essentials. Get your image looking
pretty good overall and make sure your
shots match. That's how you do it in the
color page. All right, let's talk about
fair. Fairlight works in a similar way
to the other pages here in that it
shares this timeline and when we click
into Fairlite, it goes into audio mode.
Basically, this is the interface, the
the app within Resolve to get really
crazy with your audio mixing, sound
design, and pretty much everything to do
with what you hear in Resolve. And
here's really the big thing to remember.
we have this timeline kind of unlike we
have in the color infusion page. And so
we can actually make edits in this
timeline. And when we switch back over
to the edit page, those edits are
reflected in that timeline. Okay?
Because we're really just we're working
on the same timeline. It's just a little
bit of a different interface as far as
this part goes. Any changes that we make
in the fairlight page, I'm just grabbing
these little handles to add a fade. or
if I rightclick and say clip color and
make it a different color. Any of those
changes are also going to happen on the
edit page. And there's no real
difference between adjusting some of
these things on the Fairlite page versus
the edit page. Kind of depends on just
wherever you're at, whatever is
convenient to do. But there are a couple
reasons why you'd actually want to jump
into the Fairlight page. The first one,
just being really practical. You can
make these tracks huge and you can get
really crazy with your audio. For
instance, if you want to hold alt, you
can click on this little line right
here, which is our volume line, and I
have a lot of control over my audio. You
can do stuff like this in the edit page,
but it's a little bit easier to do when
you can make the tracks really big. And
that's really a big thing with Fairlite
is you work on audio tracks in Fairlite.
It's really optimized for a lot of
tracks. So, if I go to the media pool
and open up my audio here, all of this
audio is included in our downloadable
media. And let's say I'll just start
grabbing these and throwing them in
here, making new tracks. And if we were
to play this back, it would be terrible,
but I'll at least show you kind of how
this works. When you're working with a
lot of audio and doing sound design and
everything, you're typically working
with a lot of tracks. And you can do
some really cool stuff in Fairlite. And
in some ways, these tracks are a lot
easier to manage in Fairlite. For
instance, one thing that is new in
Resolve 21 is folders. So, I can shift
select some of these tracks. So, tracks
5 through 7. Rightclick and say add
tracks to new folder. And that will put
these in a folder like this. And I can
twirl this up. And now I have this
folder of tracks that doesn't actually
exist in the edit page. See, these are
all separate tracks.
But in Fairlite, I can twirl these up or
down. And so if you have 500 tracks, you
can group them into folders. You can
even put folders inside of folders. And
so if you're an audio nerd and you like
to add a lot of sound effects and music
and hits and all kinds of stuff, this is
the place to do it. I'm just going to
get rid of this. Right click on one of
these track headers and say delete empty
tracks. So if I were going to work on
the sound for this movie, I could go up
and open my media pool. And here under
audio, I have all these sound effects.
and let's just start kind of building
the audio for this project. One thing we
can do is replace the dialogue here. So,
we have some dialogue that's kind of on
camera and there's this clip called
Malachi lines. I can double click on it
to open it up here. And just like the
source viewer in the edit page, I can
kind of go through here and then hit I
for in or I can also click this button
to set my in and O for out. And then I
can drag this down to a track and I can
adjust its position. We'll just mute
this first track here.
>> I'm here for the droid.
>> Yeah, see that works. This is going to
be our dialogue track. So, I'll just
double click on this right here and just
say DIA. That's going to be our dialogue
for our Jedi. Let's just say DIA-Jedi.
And then maybe we also have some
dialogue for the bad guy here. So, I'll
find Ryan Vio. That's the name of the
actor who played the bad guy. We'll grab
a couple of his lines.
>> Come and take it.
>> Good. We'll just drag this down here.
But I'm going to put this on a new
track. This third track.
>> Come and take it.
>> Let's rename this track dialogue dash
Sith. Sure. And now we have two tracks.
One for each of our characters. I'll
just kind of squish this track up like
this so we have a little bit more room.
And maybe since we're in this forest
environment, we want to add some
ambience. There is a forest ambience
track here.
Let's just throw this down in one of
these lower tracks.
That'll give us a good ambient track.
And we can just kind of build our whole
soundsscape by just dragging our sound
effects into our tracks like this. We'll
just add a couple more things here. We
have we have a little shot of our droid,
which we need to colorize. I'll just
rightclick and select input color space
and make sure we have that selected.
Blackmagic Design Film Gen 5. There we
go. That needs some visual effects, but
we'll just go with this for now. Find
our droid sound effects and drop that in
there again in a new track.
Great. We'll name that droid. This will
be ambience. And we just put in
everything that we want to hear. And
typically, it's a good workflow to put
all the different things on different
tracks. So your dialogue from one
character in one environment goes on one
track in a different environment might
go to a different track from a different
character is on a third track. Sound
effects from a certain source might go
on their own track. You can have as many
tracks as you want. And the advantage
here is that all of the tracks show up
here in the mixer. And it's really easy
just to move these faders up and down to
decide how loud or quiet the tracks need
to be. So for instance, this ambience
might be a little bit loud. So, I can
just take that down in the mixer
while I'm listening to it and really
kind of dial that in. Maybe that droid's
a little loud, too. We'll take that
down. But, we'll keep this dialogue.
>> I'm here for the droid
>> nice and loud.
>> Come and take it.
>> And so, we can put tracks in a physical
group like I showed you earlier, like a
folder, but we can also just run the
output of a track through what we call a
bus. A bus is like a special track that
multiple audio tracks actually route
through. And so you can apply effects or
volume or EQ or all kinds of different
effects to affect multiple tracks at
once. Now, by default, everything is
going through bus one. That is like the
main mix, the stereo mix. But if I go up
to Fairlite and go to bus format,
I can add a bus right here. And we'll
call this instead of bus 2, we'll call
this dialogue dashbus and hit okay. And
here in our mixer, if I scroll down on
my scroll wheel, I can go to where it
says bus outputs. And here for the
dialogue Jedi and dialog Sith, I can add
a bus. So this dialog bus like this.
There we go. And I'll take away I'll
just remove these bus outputs
for bus one. If I were to play this
back, we aren't going to hear it because
this is being played into a bus that
actually isn't routed to the stereo.
It's just kind of like a secondary mix.
So, both of these are playing back in
this bus, but this bus itself, we don't
actually hear it. But we can see the
meters popping up here and here. When we
play it back, it's just not coming
through the actual main output. So all
we have to do here is for bus two, we
need to make sure that has an output of
bus one. So now when we play this back,
>> come and take it.
>> We still hear our dialogue, but it's
going through bus two first. Here's
what's cool about this. I can adjust
both of these tracks
>> together
using this bus.
>> Take it
>> or put on effects. So for instance,
right here where it says effects, I can
click this little plus and I can add
something like how about some reverb.
And now whatever is being put into that
bus is going to go through this reverb.
>> So that's really really heavy reverb.
Don't probably want it that crazy.
>> But that's a way that you can add the
same effect to multiple different tracks
without just duplicating the effect a
whole bunch. Now on this same bus and in
any track actually we have a couple
really powerful features. One is this
horizontal green line which if you
double click on it is our dynamics. This
is a way to add what we call a
compressor to a track which basically
makes sure that the louder parts of the
audio aren't too loud. And there's ways
to push up the quieter parts. And a lot
of the time you can just go to this
preset up here where it says default.
I'll just switch this to dialogue level
expander. Sure.
>> Come and take it.
>> And what that's going to do is just make
sure that the loudest parts aren't too
loud. And then we can push this makeup
up and make the whole thing louder.
>> Come and take it.
>> So, this is something that we do all the
time on dialogue because it helps the
dialogue be loud enough to kind of cut
through the mix. Easy to hear when you
have, you know, terrible speakers. In
fact, my dialogue right now that you're
hearing is going through something very
similar to this to make sure that when I
talk really quietly, you can still hear
me. And when I talk really loud, it's
not too loud. The other really powerful
thing in each track is this little cyan
line, which is the EQ. Double click on
this, and that'll bring up our
equalizer. This is a way to turn up or
down certain frequencies in your audio.
So, right here, come and take it.
>> Let's actually get rid of this reverb
here for a minute.
Come and take it.
>> Maybe I'll just hit I and O to set an in
and an out on our timeline. And then
I'll loop this.
>> Come and take it.
Come and take it.
>> So we can hear it.
>> Come and take it.
>> And now check this out.
>> I can take this and make him sound like
he's in
>> another room with the door closed just
by doing this.
>> Yeah. See? Come and take it.
>> Or I can make him sound like he's on a
phone speaker.
>> Come and take it.
Come and take it. Come and take it.
>> And so you can add an EQ to any track or
a bus. Audio is a hu just a massively
huge world. But these are really the
essentials of Fairlite. You put your
audio in the various tracks. You have a
lot of controls for each track here on
the channel strips in the mixer,
including effects, dynamics, EQ, panning
controls. That's like panning it left
and right, and you can decide which bus
they go into. Not to mention, you can
mute your channels and adjust them up
and down with the mixer. There are so
many other things to show you with
Fairlite, but those are the really
essential things. Okay, so let's say
that this video looks amazing. It's
wonderful, and we're ready to render it.
The way that you do that is you go to
the deliver page. You click on that and
that's going to bring your timeline into
the deliver page and get it ready to
render. Rendering is converting your
movie from this project in Resolve to an
actual like video file that somebody can
watch or you can upload to YouTube or
share with your client or whatever you
want to do. And this is a pretty deep
world, too. But the essentials are this.
Over here on the left, you have a whole
bunch of presets that you can choose
from. There's presets for YouTube,
presets for Tik Tok, all kinds of stuff.
And you set your settings under here,
and you have settings for video and
audio, as well as your file name and
that kind of thing. And I'll show you
the most common settings because you can
just go crazy on these settings and
tweaking them all over the place. The
two long didn't read is there's
basically like two kinds of videos that
you would make. One for sharing, for
uploading to YouTube, that kind of
thing. And the other kind would be like
an archive. The YouTube version is
pretty small, a little bit compressed,
and is designed to be shared. The
archive version is a much higher quality
video, but it's a much bigger file size.
So, I'll show you how to do both. We
could get into all the details here, but
really, if you go to the presets and you
switch to H.265 master, that is going to
be a pretty darn good preset for
YouTube. Now, if you have the free
version of Resolve on a PC, you won't be
able to render H.265. In that case, I
would just recommend like a YouTube
2160p render, and that's going to give
you a pretty good result. But what I
like to do is H.265 master. And the only
thing I'm going to change is this
resolution. I'm going to make this
resolution at least UHD. Okay, 3840x
2160. Now, if I'm shooting in UHD and my
timeline settings are UHD, that's going
to work great. But even if you didn't
shoot UHD, even if you're just working
with an HD timeline, I would render this
UHD because when you upload it to
YouTube, YouTube is going to treat it
with more respect [laughter] and your
video file is going to look better.
There isn't anything magic happening
when you upscale this to ultra HD. It's
not it's not doing anything fancy. It's
just kind of tricking YouTube into
treating it better, treating it nicely.
So, H.265 master preset resolution 3840
x 2160. Add to render Q. It's going to
say, "Are you sure you want to add
higher resolution renders?" And I'm
going to say yes. I'm going to add, and
that's going to add the job to the
render queue. Now, this isn't rendering
yet. It's just kind of adding it to a
to-do list. So, that is the version that
we upload to YouTube. It's a good idea
to make an archive version of your
video. Now, what is that? That's a
highquality version that would be easy
to bring back into an editor and re-edit
at some point. It's just the highest
quality version you can make of your
video and you don't care if the file
sizes are huge. And so I'm going to go
up to preset here and I'm just going to
pick ProRes 42:2 HQ. This is a great
place to start when it comes to making
an archive version. In fact, I would
pretty much just keep all of these same
settings. The only tweak I would make is
I would go to audio right here and down
here where it says output track one, I
would switch this to all timeline
tracks. What that's going to do is
render every single track on our
timeline as a separate track in the
video file so that if you ever need to
edit this a different way, you can bring
it in and you have all of your audio
separated. So you could remove the music
or remove the sound effects or the
dialogue or replace it or something if
you need to in the future. You could
probably leave this as is. If you want a
little bit more quality, you could
switch this to like 32-bit float. Sure,
that's fine. Let's call this, you know,
movie-archive.
And I'll hit add to render Q. And now we
have both of our versions of our movies.
I can select both of these and then go
here to render all. And what that's
going to do is render both of the
versions of these movies. One of them
for YouTube and one of them for archive.
Here I am. I have my YouTube version
right here
and my archive version. If I just bring
this back into Resolve, we can see
what's up here. Rightclick, create new
timeline. We can see that we have the
video as well as the separated audio
tracks. Isn't that cool? Oh, it's going
to be so helpful in the future if I need
to re-edit this. That's the essentials
of creating a video in Resolve. Resolve
is a huge, deep program. Video creation
is a massive topic. If you're looking at
this and you're going, "Oh, wow. That's
a lot." Me and my team want to help you.
And so, I want to invite you to Ground
Control Film School. This is our
community. And what you can do is you
can make a post and post a video that
you've been working on. This is one from
our friend Sandro. and he's asking,
"What do you think about this video?"
And then every weekday, me and my team
sit down and we review the videos that
are posted to the community and we give
comments and feedback and we'll narrow
it down to one major thing that you can
do to make your videos better. Sometimes
that has to do with learning a specific
skill in Resolve. And in that case, you
can go up to our classroom and inside
the classroom, we have access to all of
our Resolve courses. So if you want to
learn fusion, we have Fusion 101, 2011,
301, practice projects. We have color
101, Fairlite 101. There is a massive
amount of resources here. And so you can
go in the classroom and dig in and nerd
out and learn all kinds of stuff. Or if
you want to keep things simple, you can
just go and study the lessons that we
suggest. Then it's not overwhelming or
frustrating. You're just always working
on the right things to make the most
progress in your video creation. We're
seeing people who were making videos
that were kind of meh actually make
videos that are really great. They're
making huge progress in a matter of like
days and weeks instead of years. And the
cool thing is that can be your story,
too. All you got to do is sign up and
you'll have me and my team behind you
helping you. And so, you don't have to
be overwhelmed or lost or frustrated.
You're just constantly working on the
things that are really important. And
you constantly have a clear path to
always be working on the big stuff
that's really going to make a difference
in your videos. If this sounds like a
good time, there is a link in the
description down below. That's a special
invite to Ground Control Film School. I
want to see you in there. And again, if
you want some media to follow along,
well, how how about there? How about how
about you can get that media for free?
That's all the Star Wars media. And you
can just have a great time playing
around, making some edits, doing some
audio, some color grading, even some
fusion stuff, making some lightsabers.
Oh, baby. Hey, thanks for hanging out
with me. I'll see you later.